A Guide to the Francis Jerdone Papers, 1783-1822
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Francis Jerdone Papers, 1783-1822
Library of Virginia
21466
25 leaves (negative photostats).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Philip Padelford, New Haven, Connecticut. 14 December 1938.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Jerdone was born 9 February 1756 at "Jerdone Castle" in Louisa County, Virgina. He was the son of Francis Jerdone (1720/1-1771), a prominent Scottish merchant, and Sarah Macon Jerdone (1731/2-1818). A successful planter and merchant, Jerdone inherited the estate upon his father's death in 1771, but may have almost lost it during the American Revolution. Jerdone was reputedly a tory, but his mother was a friend of Martha Washington, and "Jerdone Castle" was never confiscated. George Washington stayed there in 1791. Jerdone married Mary "Polly" Byars (1781-1821) 20 June 1799 and he died at "Jerdone Castle" 29 April 1841.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1783-1822, of Francis Jerdone (1756-1841) of Louisa County, Virginia, consisting of correspondence from Dr. Robert B. Honeyman (1752-1822) of Hanover County, Virginia, concerning the health and medical treatment of Jerdone's family and slaves, as well as payment for magazine subscriptions. Also includes accounts and receipts for both the medical treatment and magazine subscriptions.
Contents List
- Account. [Francis] Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, August and October 1783. Receipt dated 16 February 1784., 1 p. (Print 1)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, August 1797 - January 1798. Receipt dated 14 June 1798.
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 7 August 1797., 1 p. (Print 6)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 19 September 1797., 1 p. (Print 4)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 24 November 1797., 1 p. (Print 5)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, n.p., 24 December 1797., 1 p. (Print 2)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, February and June 1799. Receipt dated 8 October 1799., 1 p. (Print 1)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, May, August, and September 1800. Receipt dated 7 January 1801., 1 p. (Print 7)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 24 January 1801., 2 p. (Prints 9, 10)
- Account. Robert Honeyman with Francis Jerdone, 25 January 1801 - 19 March 1802. Receipt dated 24 July 1802., 1 p. (Print 8)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 13 June 1805., 1 p. (Print 11)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 8 August 1805., 1 p. (Print 12)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, November 1806 and January 1807. Receipt dated 31 December 1807., 1 p. (Print 16)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 19 June 1807., 1 p. (Print 15)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 31 December 1807., 2 p. (Prints 13, 14)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, 10 July 1808 - 14 December 1809. Receipt dated 23 January 1810., 2 p. (Print 17)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, 17 February 1810 - 15 October 1814. Receipt dated 25 December 1814, 1 p. (Print 18)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 2 January 1811, 1 p. (Print 19)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman, 12 May - 26 September 1815. Receipt dated 18 December 1815., 1 p. (Print 23)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 20 November 1815., 1 p. (Print 23)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, "Kinneff", [Hanover County], to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 30 November 1816., 1 p. (Print 21)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman and son, 24 January - 24 May 1818. Receipt dated 11 August 1818., 1 p. (Print 22)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman and son, 22 June - 22 November 1819. Receipt dated by Robert Honeyman 19 June 1820., 2 p. (Print 22)
- Account. Francis Jerdone with Robert Honeyman and son, 16 February 1820 - 1 March 1821. Receipt dated 11 January 1822., 1 p. (Print 25)
- Letter. Robert Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, n.p. 25 January 1821., 1 p. (Print 23)
- Letter. Robert B. Honeyman, n.p., to Francis Jerdone, Sr., n.p., 23 November 1821., 1 p. (Print 24)